So, thank you again folks for joining.
Uh, it's August 28th, 2025. This is
cohort 8. We're starting the second half
of the textbook reading group. And we
know from the first chapter that uh the
the structure of the book is such that
the second half of the book is dedicated
much more to applying active inference
yourself to your own research as opposed
to the first half which is more about
setting up the kind of theoretical
framework and and concepts and
introducing you from things to what is a
generative model, a generative process,
what are action, perception
What is the relationship of all of this
to things like um theories of predictive
processing to to the brazian basian
brain hypothesis? We had the low road
and the high road to active inference.
Um and and so it's here in the second
half of the book that we're going to
start learning how to actually apply
this. It does mean that we will be
getting uh much more in depth about u
particular simulations
uh and and models and and fitting models
to to empirical data. Um it means like
actually looking at simulations and and
code and models that were already
produced by the publication of this
textbook and using them as sort of
illustrative examples of some of the
exemplar models that are used in active
inference. uh not just to adhere to
what's already been done, but to kind of
provide us with a foundation on which we
can uh build going forward uh for our
own work. Um and so I've shared my
screen. This is a bit of a throwback to
a previous chapter, but it's just a fair
reminder given that chapter 6 is a
recipe for designing active inference
models. um that whenever we kind of
start out with considering like how
should we build a model um what what is
the work that's that's going to be
entailed in any kind of project that
applies these kinds of principles. Um
first we recognize like we have what is
the generative model or the agent. Those
might be used kind of interchangeably
throughout the textbook. And then on the
other hand, we have the environment or
the generative process. Um, and as we
know from previous chapters, they're
separated by a kind of uh marov blanket
boundary. And so at at no point does the
agent necessarily have to have a model
that is equivalent to the generative
process. Um I I sometimes uh and forgive
me but I'll sometimes use kind of silly
analogies but um you know someone's
saying knock on wood uh as an idiom that
we use often to say like you know one
does that for luck or by chance or
something along those lines. It might be
the case that knocking on wood, the
action of that maybe consoles the person
based on the beliefs they have about
that idiom and and and and how that
maybe changes going forward how they
view the situation because now they feel
better that they knocked on wood or some
kind of tick that they're they're trying
to resolve for themselves or otherwise.
Even though knocking on wood may not
actually do anything to the generative
process, actually it it might be in this
case in the sense that it is impacting
your own behavior going forward. Um, but
there's no necessity that always
knocking on wood actually aligns with
some kind of real phenomena or
generative process uh in reality outside
of yourself. Right? So um that's kind of
a crude example but it's just to say
that whenever you set up a model there
is no there's no necessity that it be
entirely vertical to um the generative
process in which it finds itself. Um and
and anyone who engages in things like
machine learning or deep learning or
otherwise and works with very large
models, blackbox models, etc. like
they're they're more focused upon a
certain kind of model architecture that
allows for certain kinds of inference
without it necessarily having any kind
of onetoone interpretability with the
environment. Right? So we have 7 billion
uh hyperparameters uh for example you
know some kind of very complex model
that's very difficult to to parse out.
Um
and in any case so that this is just
laying out a kind of recipe. The idea is
well um first which system are we
modeling? So later we'll get into
examples of uh the kind of classic um
mouse in a team uh example. So in that
case it's very quick to kind of intuit
it that the the agent here is the mouse
and the environment is the teammates and
everything else in which the the agent
finds itself. Right? So that kind of
aligns with the the image. You know the
person's head here is now our mouse. the
world is the T-mas and the the stimuli
within and so on. Um and um secondly,
what is the most appropriate form for
the generative model? That's going to to
require consideration over what kind of
simulation are you building? Uh what is
your agent doing? What is what is the
context of what it is you're trying to
build in uh chapter 7? So the in in that
in that case the the mouse uh kind of
begins at a starting point in a T-mase
and it has three different things it can
do. It can either uh move to the left
arm of the T-mase or move to the right
arm of the T-mase or it can move to uh
the back of the T-mas that has an
informative cue. Um, if it does that,
then it gets an observation that kind of
gives it a strong hint uh that the the
stimuli it wants, which likened to a
reward in reinforcement learning or more
literally we could say it's some kind of
cheese or or some kind of
sweet substance or otherwise it might be
used in an actual laboratory. Uh so the
the mouse has these three discrete
options and it moves to three discrete
locations. Uh it collects either a
positive stimuli that being the cheese
or a negative stimuli that being some
kind of you know potentially
negative shock or something that it
doesn't like. Uh so so in that case
we're looking at uh kind of a discrete
state space, right? We're not looking at
necessarily like what what what does the
mouse see in its visual field and and
sampling from the environment around it
in a sense that it has to look through
some large visual field and and pick out
particular things and then some large
continuous state space. It's much more
discretized than that. It's also much
more amendable to doing different kinds
of uh and much easier to fit that
behaviorally, right? Because if you were
doing this in reality, you could track
did the mouse move left, did it move
right? Just much simpler than than
having to say like what particular angle
at what acceleration did it move in this
precise direction. Um so that all of
that is to say and that's a leadup into
chapter seven which will be on discrete
models. chapter eight which will be on
continuous models that active inference
of course can confront either one of
those scenarios and forms of state
spaces and ways of kind of uh chopping
up or not time uh in terms of collecting
like you know if you have a a discrete
simulation that runs over discrete time
steps versus a simulation that involves
continuous streams of of data. you can
already begin to imagine how these kinds
of models could be applied to a broad
variety of phenomena, not just you know
mice and te- mases. Um in any case, so
we think of what is the most appropriate
form of the generative model. I already
mentioned discrete continuous. Should
there be a kind of hierarchical
construction in which case maybe there's
um a model at a lower level that more
directly interfaces with the environment
versus some higher level uh model that's
maybe related to planning or you know
decision making. Um you know kind of
example would be you know the lower
level could be the eyes that are
visually sampling an environment. a
higher level something related to
reasoning. The prefrontal cortex,
however it is that you find it best to
kind of find a coralate for that could
then be what decides uh you know a kind
of discrete uh object it is seeing
within the visual field as the data is
sampled from the lower level. So that's
the that's this kind of hierarchical
message passing process could then work
with both continuous and uh discrete
data. Um I'm particularly fond of those.
Um and so so once you decide what is the
form of the model, what what what is the
mouse in your in the case of of what
you're setting up, then how do you after
you set up the generative model, how do
you set up the generative process? Well,
um we already are considering with the
teammates like, well, we have a left
arm, we have a right arm, we have an
informative cue. So, you're just
thinking of all of these different
things that the environment itself kind
of elicits um you know, it elicits uh a
cue. If the agent moves to the space
where there is a queue, it elicits
positive stimuli in the left arm if
that's indeed where it should be. So,
this I really like this image just
because of the kind of reciprocal aspect
of of the the environment elicits
observations and the agent makes
predictions and carries out actions. Uh
sometimes I phrase it as an action uh an
agent's action is the environment's
observation and the environment's action
is the agent's observation. It's a
really nice way to suddenly we have this
isomorphic relationship between an agent
environment. You could also think of
that as an agent and another agent,
right? Um and then you could just blow
that up and have, you know, 30 or 100
agents within an environment. You have
all of these sort of loops going on
between them. Um so that's that's sort
of the th those are kind of the key
topics here. Um I
there are already different things
implied implied in what I said regarding
like time scales of inference. Um this
is related to some things in previous
chapters but oftentimes in cases of
learning um the one mo if you have a
hierarchical model for example the lower
level might learn faster than the than
the higher model and so the higher order
model kind of modulates uh the lower
order model um different kinds of
constructions like that. So
well for sharing we'll uh just given the
time uh we'll kind of open it up from
there and uh cuz it's th this chapter is
really just setting things up for anyone
who already does computational modeling.
None of this is going to be incredibly
surprising to read uh for for anyone who
who wants to set up a model. These are
these are the kind of questions they're
thinking about. It's just kind of
putting it in the framework of active
inference thinking like we're thinking
generative processes and beliefs and
states and so on. So, um, yeah. Did, um,
so Benjamin, did you have any kind of
questions? For example, not to put you
on the spot, but
>> no, no major questions. I this I
remember this diagram from chapter 2,
which is all I've read through so far.
So, this is relevant to Yeah. what I was
reading. It makes sense. No major
questions. And I had just shared in the
chat like a similar diagram that I
reminded you of.
>> Cool. Might check that out.
See
just
world is system selfsynthesized by
quantum networking.
Yeah,
>> just in terms of it being like a closed
loop or something, but that's a much
older paper. It's from 1980.
>> 1980. Gotcha. I mean, it's
>> Yeah. 88.
>> 88. It it's it's so interesting that
like like if you if you ever decide to
take the time to kind of like skim
around chapter 10, which arguably should
be chapter 2 in my opinion, possibly. Uh
but cuz chapter 10 is this sort of outro
chapter, but really what it does is that
it it makes all these statements about
the relationship between active
inference and other fields. just sort of
in the spirit of making it clear that
this is a a very interdisciplinary
framework. Um I mean it it draws from
principles of of cybernetics and control
theory. Um we have aspects of of biology
and reinforcement learning relationships
with economics.
>> And I only found this paper reading
through like some Santa Fe Institute
book of book of like good papers over
the years and kind of chasing down a
citation. So that that also exposed me
to how interdisciplinary it can be.
>> Nice. Yeah. Yeah. For sure. I mean all
these things are implicated and so I
mean anyone who tries to to to model
vision in in active inference we are
looking at things like the retina. We're
looking at light. we're looking at um
you know movement and and and so there
are a lot of attempts to kind of if you
if you want to model a phenomenon
um people will set up for a generative
process or environment like an entire
you know set of kind of like physics in
a in a simulation. So like um being able
to simulate a a car accelerating up and
down a a you know
elevated plane that's at an angle such
that there's friction and so on. Um I
mean all of these it's just kind of that
uh that nice philosophical sort of like
everything in the in the universe is
interconnected. Uh but and yet we're
trying to zoom in on a piece of it uh
and model it as we can. And I I think
it's that um the concept of the mar of
blanket which you'll find in
I believe it's introduced roughly around
chapter three or four but it's it's it
starts to kind of pervade the first half
of the book as you go forward. But um in
some ways the idea of a markup blanket
is kind of a useful tool for trying to
say like well how do we delimmit the
agent or how do we delimmit the the
phenomenon of interest I'm looking at
and the environment around.
Um so yeah
>> I'll peek ahead to chapter 10 and since
you said it might be appropriate for
chapter 2. Thanks for riffing on that.
>> Yeah absolutely. I like pointing people
to it because whenever you're getting
into active inference, it's like you're
coming from somewhere. Um, Daniel came
here through uh an entomology studying
uh ants and biology and I came here
through through social science and an
interest in kind of clinical uh
psychotherapy and psychiatry. So it's
just it it was useful for me to get to
here through and then continued making
me more interested um whenever I came
here through more neuroscience and was
looking at neuroiming data and then I
was like oh Fristen uh and company
really get it um the way that they're
trying to actually use findings from
neuroscience to inform kind of bigger
questions as well as giving a framework
for doing computational modeling with
that that Pier24 lacks a lot of kind of
standard methods or frameworks and
people just kind of have their own
background and if they can't find a way
of unifying those backgrounds at least
to some degree it makes it much more
difficult to have
sort of like interdisciplinary
dialogues. So
yeah,
um I think we'll
it's completely okay if we wrap up uh a
bit early this time. We still let Ryan
had to head out. Um,
so
>> I do actually have one more question
based on what you were saying, which was
like when you were talking about the
maze, you were talking about a
informative Q and I guess my question is
like I think I understand what you're
saying, but you mean the letter Q,
right? Or do you mean a QE?
>> Gotcha. No. Yeah, sorry. It it'd be c U.
It's um
>> ah, okay. Well, that makes sense as
well. I thought you might might be there
might be some jargon that is a thing
called informative that is symbolized as
cute but now I also understand what you
mean by cu
>> yeah no for sure it's it's a good um
it's I mean while doing that kind of
like a mouse in a team example I mean
it's been you know it's been done many
many times over in actual laboratories
and empirical work um but it's not just
used in this book to say like everyone
needs to care about this kind of
paradigm uh and and care about mice
behavior. But uh here it's simply to
it's a good example of it's an agent.
The agent has multiple options available
to it or things that it can do. Um and
yet whenever we get into notions of
planning and expected free energy which
you'll start to come upon if not already
in chapter 2 three
>> yeah it it's it's there and this is the
thing that was very interesting to me
coming also from a slight like
reinforcement learning agent-based
modeling background was um
um an agent who is driven to explore and
find more information and minimize its
uncertainty even though the action it's
taking doesn't necessarily lead ex like
expressly to a reward. Um, so I'm not
sure on your familiarity with those kind
any of those kinds of problems, but it's
sort of like the explore exploit
dilemma, which is a a very classic kind
of debate in uh in social science for
sure, but it's it's it's it's
big in in reinforcement learning and
machine learning generally because
whenever a model gets stuck in a local
optima
um like you know it's found a suboptimal
solution to a problem, but it doesn't
know how to get out of that because it's
learned to do, you know, um, in standard
reinforcement learning, it's basically
it's learned the best thing it can do
given what it's been through thus far.
So, why do anything else? Why doesn't
why doesn't a human being just, you
know, stay in a dark room as much as
possible and minimize all of their
uncertainty and, you know, eat food and
and that's it. And, you know, they don't
move on further beyond that. And um so
expected free energy viewed just kind of
mathematically as like an algorithm. It
it it has kind of an exploration term
within it instead of it having to be a
kind of hardcoded rule which is
sometimes done in reinforcement
learning. It'll say like you know the
it's much more sophisticated nowadays
but still sometimes people rely on like
oh have the agent do something random
10% of the time. uh just just have them
do something random. Uh just so that
because
>> entropy or entropy I guess in injection
just to prevent
>> Yeah.
>> optimal stability or something.
>> Yeah, it's like a it's like a it's like
an odd uh I would call it a band-aid,
but it's uh it's not necessarily helpful
in all cases. Um but uh so so yeah with
with expected free energy it's like we
you have within the algorithm a term
that can differentiate relative to the
model because everything is kind of
relative to the model in active
inference and modeling in general um you
know it it it it
learns about its policies and so by
eliciting new observations through
trying new policies that it hasn't
really tried before or maybe it hasn't
tried them in particular contexts. Um it
it it effectively tries it it estimates
through inference what is the
information gain that I get out of doing
this. And um the the claim in the book
which is slightly misspoken is that um
information gain and and pragmatic value
which you can think of as just going
directly to a reward. Um it they get
naturally balanced. They're not actually
necessarily balanced in all cases, but
the point is that both are computed
simultaneously. And so you can score any
any possible policy in active inference
with with exploration and exploitation
kind of combined. So there is no
arbitrary
rule here going on. There are no
band-aids. Um it's just kind of kind of
baked in. um could that get the agent
theoretically into trouble? Maybe. Uh
children make mistakes all the time, but
uh is one funny way of phrasing that.
But um yeah, so that's that's to me
that's been one of the biggest sort of
like oh like I I appreciate this entire
notion and if it's if it could be traced
back to any kind of empirical work
that's been done um or with neuroiming
data or behavioral data or otherwise
then you know I it's honestly one of the
best ways of handling that explore
exploit dilemma that I can possibly
think of up to this point in time. So,
um, that's sort of my take, but
>> thank you. And you have to run to this
other meeting, but I appreciate your
help and added context and tips. So,
hopefully see you at the next one.
>> Yeah, absolutely. Thanks for thanks for
stopping by. We'll see you next time.
Bye. Well, take care.